A Guide to the Records of the Arlington County Council of PTAs, 1949-2003
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Records of the Arlington County Council of PTAs, 1949-2003
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 183
14 boxes.
Arlington County Council of PTAs
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Lawrence Fishtahler in July 2010.
Historical Information
RG 183 houses the records of the Arlington (Virginia) Council of PTAs (CCPTA). The CCPTA comprises local PTA units from 22 elementary schools, four middle schools, and three high schools in Arlington County. The mission is to promote the goals of PTA: supporting and speaking on behalf of school children, helping parents be effective guardians and role models for their children, and encouraging greater parental involvement in their schools. CCPTA provides leadership, assists, and acts as a resource for local PTAs, helping them to work more effectively for their schools and communities. The Council was organized in 1931, although records of the early years are no longer extant, according to a history compiled in 1949 (Series 1, File 19).
The CCPTA is governed by the bylaws of the Virginia PTA. Local PTAs join the CCPTA as self-governing organizations.
Scope and Content
RG 183 measures approximately 6.5 linear feet and dates from 1949 to 2003 (bulk dates 1990-2002). Types of material include agendas, minutes, correspondence, reports, newsletters, subject files, and miscellaneous printed matter.
The records concern topics of interest to Arlington PTAs during the periods covered. The most popular include school budgets, teacher salaries, school boundaries, school annual and daily schedules, school transportation and safe routes to school, curricula, diversifying school populations, Virginia Standards of Learning, summer activities, family involvement activities, school overcrowding, PTA program planning, Virginia education legislation, and activities of the Virginia PTA.
Arrangement
Record Group 183 is organized into six series by date spans, the collection's original organization. Under each series there are files by subjects, the original arrangement. As much as possible, the original subject labels are used, even when this causes slight variations in subject terminology between series. Note that there are several date gaps (e.g. 1992, 1996). Folders containing photographs have an asterisk [*] after the file name.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Researchers interested in Arlington County schools may consult such records as: RG 163, Records of the Arlington County School Board and RG 7, Records of the Arlington County Public Schools.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Parent-teacher relationships -- United States.; Education -- Virginia -- Arlington County (Va.); Arlington (Va.); Arlington County (Va.)
Contents List
- Records Chiefly 1990-1991
  - ACI (Advisory Council on Instruction), 1989-1991 (Box 1)
  - Accreditation, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Appointments, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Budgets, 1986-1991 (Box 1)
  - Chairman Information, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Chairman's Council, 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Clothing Bank, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Communication, 1984-1991 (Box 1)
  - Community Organizations, 1986-1991 (Box 1)
  - County Councilor, 1988-1990 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum 1986-1991 (Box 1)
  - Desegregation, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
  - Diverse Population Aids (Box 1)
  - Diverse Populations, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Drug Abuse, 1987 (Box 1)
  - Forum, 1988-1989 (Box 1)
  - Grade Reporting, 1985-1990 (Box 1)
  - Health and Wellness, 1985-1990 (Box 2)
  - History - Arlington CCPTAs, 1949, 1989 (Box 2)
  - Installations (Box 2)
  - Insurance, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Legislation 1986-1991 (Box 2)
  - Local Units, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Media, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Middle Schools,, 1989-1991 (Box 2)
  - Minority Achievement, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - National PTA, 1989-1991 (Box 2)
  - Planning Factors, 1986, 1989-1991 (Box 2)
  - Potomac District, 1990-1991 (Box 2)
  - Priority Areas of Work, 1987-1990 (Box 3)
  - Reflections, 1988-1991 (Box 3)
  - Salary Study, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Scholarship, 1989-1990 (Box 3)
  - Seven Period Day, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - Six-Year Plan, 1986-1991 (Box 3)
  - State PTA, 1990-1991 (Box 3)
  - Strategic Plan, 1983-1991 (Box 3)
  - Taxes, 1983-1991 (Box 3)
  - Transportation, 1988-1990 (Box 3)
- Records Chiefly 1993-1995
  - AEA, 1993-1994 (Box 3)
  - Assessment, 1993-1994 (Box 3)
  - Budget, 1994-1995 (Box 3)
  - Candidate Forum, 1994-1995 (Box 3)
  - Charter Schools, 1994-1995 (Box 3)
  - Class Size, 1994 (Box 3)
  - County Council Budget, 1993-1995 (Box 3)
  - County Council (General), 1993-1995 (Box 4)
  - County Councilor, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Expanding Role, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Goals 2000 for Virginia SOLs, 1995 (Box 4)
  - Hit the Ground, 1993 (Box 4)
  - Leadership Workshop: 12 Angry Men, 1993-1994 * (Box 4)
  - Letters to President and County Council Delegate, 1993-1995 (Box 4)
  - Mainstreaming, 1993-1994 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1994-1995 (Box 4)
  - Parent Involvement Profiles/PIC, 1993-1995 (Box 4)
  - Peacemaking and Safety, 1994-1995 (Box 4)
  - "Process," 1995 (Box 4)
  - Quality Education Case Studies, 1994-1995 (Box 4)
  - Reflections, 1994-1995 (Box 5)
  - State/National, 1993-1995 (Box 5)
  - Summer, 1994-1995 (Box 5)
  - Technology, 1993-1995 (Box 5)
  - Winter Reception, 1994 (Box 5)
- Records Chiefly 1997-1998
  - Addresses and Telephone Numbers, 1997-1998 (Box 5)
  - Alternative Admissions, 1997-1998 (Box 5)
  - Announcements - Information, 1997-1998 (Box 5)
  - Arlington Public Schools Handbook, 1997-1998 (Box 5)
  - Banquet, 1997-1998 (Box 5)
  - Banquet, 1989-1992 (Box 5)
  - Banquet, 1998 (Box 5)
  - Budget Proposal for 1999 FY, 1998 (Box 6)
  - Building Level Management Plans, 1997-1998 (Box 6)
  - Calendar, 1997-1998 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence for County Council of PTAs, 1998 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence for PTA Presidents, 1997-1998 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence for School Board, 1998 (Box 6)
  - County Councilor, 1994-1998 (Box 6)
  - Directory, 1997-1998 (Box 6)
  - ESL Report, 1995-1997 (Box 6)
  - Family Information Center (Box 6)
  - Fund Raising, 1997 (Box 6)
  - The Gap, 1997-1998 (Box 6)
  - Glossary, 1997-1998 (Box 6)
  - Indoor Air Quality, 1994, 1996, 1997 (Box 6)
  - Latino Parent Training, 1997-1998 (Box 6)
  - Legislation, 1997-1998 (Box 6)
  - Outreach, 1995, 1997-1998 (Box 6)
  - Overcrowding - General, 1990-1997 (Box 6)
  - Overcrowding - Middle School, 1997-1998 (Box 7)
  - Partners in Education, 1997-1998 (Box 7)
  - Press Releases, 1997-1998 (Box 7)
  - Programs, 1996-1998 (Box 7)
  - Read Across America, 1998 (Box 7)
  - Reflections, 1997-1998 (Box 7)
  - Second Language Instruction, 1998 (Box 7)
  - SOA/SOL, 1997-1998 (Box 7)
  - State, 1997-1998 (Box 7)
  - Superintendent, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Technology, 1996, 1997 (Box 7)
  - Treasurer, 1996-1997 (Box 7)
  - Web Page (County Council of PTAs) (Box 7)
- Records Chiefly 1998-1999
  - Budget - County Council of PTAs, 1998-1999 (Box 7)
  - Budget - Arlington Schools, 1998-1999 (Box 7)
  - Budget, Arlington Schools, Superintendent Proposed Budget FY 2000, 1999 (Box 7)
  - Bylaws, 1994, 1997, 1999 (Box 8)
  - Calendar, 1998, 1999 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1998-1999 (Box 8)
  - County Councilor, 1998-1999 (Box 8)
  - Crowding, 1997-1999 (Box 8)
  - FAcilities, Accommodations, 1999 (Box 8)
  - Legislation, 1998-1999 (Box 8)
  - Meetings - County Council of PTAs, 1997-1999 (Box 8)
  - National PTA, 1998-1999 (Box 8)
  - National PTA - Annual Resources for PTAs, 1998-1999 (Box 8)
  - Neighborhood Day, 1998 (Box 9)
  - Parental Involvement, 1998 (Box 9)
  - Partners in Education, 1998 (Box 9)
  - Press, 1998 (Box 9)
  - Programs, 1998-1999 (Box 9)
  - School Board, 1998 (Box 9)
  - School Board, 1999 (Box 9)
  - Summer Activities Fair - Teen Summer Expo, 1999 (Box 9)
  - Survey Results v. 1, by Mathtech, 1999 (Box 9)
  - Virginia PTA, 1999 (Box 9)
  - Youth Task Force, 1998 (Box 9)
- Records Chiefly 2000-2001
  - Agendas, September 1999 - June 2000 (Box 10)
  - Agenda and Supporting Documents, August 7, 2000 (Box 10)
  - Agenda and Supporting Documents, September 6, 2000 (Box 10)
  - Agenda and Supporting Documents, September 18, 2000 (Box 10)
  - Agenda and Supporting Documents (Includes Bylaws), October 2, 2000 (Box 10)
  - Suporting Documents for Meeting, October 16, 2000 (Box 10)
  - Agenda and Supporting Documents, November 6, 2000 (Box 10)
  - Agenda and Supporting Documents, November 20, 2000 (Box 10)
  - Agenda and Supporting Documents, January 3, 2001 (Box 10)
  - Agenda and Supporting Documents, January 22, 2001 (Box 10)
  - Agenda and Supporting Documents, February 5, 2001 (Box 10)
  - Agenda and Supporting Documents, February 26, 2001 (Box 10)
  - Agenda and Supporting Documents, March 5, 2001 (Box 10)
  - Agenda and Supporting Documents, April 2, 2001 (Box 10)
  - Agenda and Supporting Documents, May 7, 2001 (Box 10)
  - Banquet, May 21, 2001 (Box 10)
  - Bond Campaign, 1998 (Box 10)
  - Bond Campaign, 2000 (Box 10)
  - Boundaries, March 2000 (Box 10)
  - Budget, 2000-2001 (Box 10)
  - Calendars, 2000-2001 (Box 10)
  - Contacts, 2000-2001 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, April - August 2000 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, September 2000 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, October - December 2000 (Box 10)
  - County Councilor, 1999-2001 (Box 11)
  - District, 2000 (Box 11)
  - Facilities Proposal for FY 2002-2007, 2000 (Box 11)
  - Forum, February - March 2001 (Box 11)
  - Greatergood.com 2000 (Box 11)
  - Kindergarten Info Night, February 7, 12, 2001 (Box 11)
  - Immersion, May 2001 (Box 11)
  - Leadership Arlington, February 2001 (Box 11)
  - Leadership Workshop, June 5, 2000 (Box 11)
  - LULAC, July 2000 (Box 11)
  - Minutes, March - June 2000 (Box 11)
  - Minutes, Arlington Forum, October 16, 2000 (Box 11)
  - Outreach, August 2000 (Box 11)
  - Partnership, 2000-2001 (Box 11)
  - PIE (Box 11)
  - PTA Meeting Schedules, 2000 (Box 11)
  - Presidents and Delegates of PTAs, 2000-2001 (Box 11)
  - Pre-School, January 2001 (Box 11)
  - Reflections, 2000-2001 (Box 11)
  - Safe Route, 2000 (Box 11)
  - School Visits, 2000 (Box 11)
  - Standards of Learning, 1999-2000 (Box 11)
  - Start Time, 2000 (Box 11)
  - Summer Activities Fair, 2001 (Box 11)
  - Superintendent, 2000 (Box 12)
  - Teacher Compensation, 2001 (Box 12)
  - Williamsburg Middle School, November 2000 (Box 12)
- Records Chiefly 2001-2002 2001-2002
  - Agenda, Leadership Workshop, June 4, 2001 (Box 12)
  - Agenda, July 16, 2001 (Box 12)
  - Agenda, September 5, 2001 (Box 12)
  - Agenda, September 24, 2001 (Box 12)
  - Agenda, October 1, 2001 (Box 12)
  - Agenda, October 15, 2001 (Box 12)
  - Agenda, November 5, 2001 (Box 12)
  - Agenda, November 19, 2001 (Box 12)
  - Agenda, January 7, 2002 (Box 12)
  - Agenda, January 28, 2002 (Box 12)
  - Agenda, February 4, 2002 (Box 12)
  - Agendas, February 19, 25, 2002 (Box 12)
  - Agenda, March 4, 2002 (Box 12)
  - Agenda, April 15, 2002 (Box 12)
  - Boundary Developement and Program Planning, 2002-2003 (Box 12)
  - Budge, 2001-2003 (Box 12)
  - Calendars, 2001-2002 (Box 13)
  - County Councilor, 2001 (Box 13)
  - Directory, 2001-2002 (Box 13)
  - District, 2001-2002 (Box 13)
  - Greater Good, 2000 (Box 13)
  - Immersion, 2000 (Box 13)
  - Information Nights, 2001-2002 (Box 13)
  - Legislative Issues, 2001-2002 (Box 13)
  - Minutes, September 2002 (Box 13)
  - Minutes, October 2002 (Box 13)
  - Minutes, November 2002 (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous, 2000 (Box 13)
  - Name Tents, 2001 (Box 13)
  - Newscheck, November 2002 (Box 13)
  - President and Delegates, 2001-2002 (Box 13)
  - Programs, 2001-2002 (Box 13)
  - Reflections, January 28, 2002 (Box 13)
  - Safety, 2000-2001 (Box 13)
  - School Board, 2001 (Box 13)
  - School Board, Novemer 21, 2002 (Box 14)
  - Arlington Traditional School Additions and Renovations, November 21, 2002 (Box 14)
  - School Board, Part 1, December 5, 2002 (Box 14)
  - School Board, Part 2, December 5, 2002 (Box 14)
  - School Board, Part 3, December 5, 2002 (Box 14)
  - School Board, December 11, 2002 (Box 14)
  - School Yard Classroom, 2002 (Box 14)
  - Sumer Activities, 2000-2002 (Box 14)
  - Teacher Pay, 2001 (Box 14)
  - TEI Video, January 31, 2002 (Box 14)
  - Virginia PTA, 2001 (Box 14)